Now let's first talk about what is a project scope.
لنتحدث الآن أولًا عن ماهية نطاق المشاريع.
Once you agree to work with the client,
بمجرد موافقتك على العمل مع عميل
the first thing that you need to discuss and preferably
أول شيء تحتاج إلى مناقشته ويفضل
document is what exactly you will be working on,
توثيقه هو الشيء الذي سوف تعمل عليه تحديدًا،
which is called the project scope.
وهذا هو ما نطلق عليه نطاق العمل.
Now, a project scope would usually entail two things.
غالبًا ما ينطوي نطاق العمل على أمران.
First, what is the final goal of the project,
أولًا، ما هو الهدف النهائي للمشروع،
the expected output of the work,
أو النتيجة المتوقعة من العمل
and second, what needs to be done to reach this goal?
وثانيًا، ما الذي تحتاج لفعله لتحقيق هذا الهدف؟
What are the building blocks,
ما هي العناصر الأساسية،
things like features of the solution or
الأشياء مثل ميزات الحل أو
work-streams that the clients wants you to work on?
مسارات العمل - التي يريدك العميل أن تعمل عليها؟
Now, it's important to keep in mind here that
من المهم هنا أن تتذكر أن
a project scope is a document that is given to a freelancer to work on.
نطاق العمل هو وثيقة تُعطى للموظف الحر ليعمل عليها.
You can, of course, help the client writer project scope, but ideally,
يمكنك بالطبع أن تساعد العميل في كتابة نطاق العمل، ولكن في الأغلب
it's the business that knows best what work needs to be done, and hence,
إنه العمل الذي يعرف أفضل ما يجب القيام به، وبالتالي،
it is ideal for it to either come from
فالوضع المثالي هو أن تأتي هذه الوثيقة منه
them or is written in active collaboration with them.
أو أن تُكتب بمشاركة فعالة معه.
Let's see a few examples to make this more clear.
لنرى بضعة أمثلة لتوضيح هذا الأمر بشكل أفضل.
Let's say you're building a web application,
لنقل أنك تنشئ تطبيق ويب
which is your end goal.
وأن هذا هو هدفك النهائي.
The project scope will include the features that need to be built,
إذًا سوف يتضمن نطاق العمل الخواص التي تحتاج لبناءها
like the authentication module,
مثل نموذج التحقق
a chatbot perhaps,
أو ربما روبوت للدردشة
a module to automatically send emails to users, and so on.
أو نموذج لإرسال رسائل البريد الإلكتروني للمستخدمين أوتوماتيكيًا، وهكذا.
If you're working on a digital marketing project for a website,
إذا كنت تعمل على مشروع للتسويق الرقمي لموقع إلكتروني
this will include the different work streams along with
فسوف يتضمن هذا مسارات العمل المختلفة إلى جانب
their details like search engine optimization,
تفاصيل تلك المسارات، مثل تحسين محركات البحث
social media campaigns, Twitter ads, and so on.
وحملات منصات التواصل الاجتماعي وإعلانات Twitter وما إلى ذلك.
If you are working in DevOps,
إذا كنت تعمل في الـ DevOps
then tasks like ability to start 20 servers automatically on the Cloud,
فسوف تتضمن مهامك القدرة على تشغيل 20 خادم على السحابة تلقائيًا،
shut down those servers automatically,
أو إغلاق هذه الخوادم تلقائيًا،
build cleanup scripts to run after a server task is completed, and so on.
أو بناء نصوص التنظيف لكي تعمل بعد إتمام مهمة خادم ما، وما إلى ذلك.
This is a high-level description of what a project scope is,
كان هذا وصفًا عالي المستوى لماهية نطاق المشروع
and some examples of it.
مع بعض الأمثلة عليه.
In the rest of the lesson,
خلال بقية الدرس،
you will see us coming back to the project scope
ستجدنا نرجع إلى نطاق العمل
and how it is so important in a client's project.
وكيف أنه شيئًا مهمًا لمشروع العميل.